Montclair, N.J., Watchung Congregational Church records, 1903-1982.
Congregational Library & Archives
Montclair, N.J., Watchung Congregational Church records, 1903-1982.
RG0715
Congregational Library & Archives
1.44 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
In 1903, the Watchung Congregational Church emerged out of the need for a Congregational church around Watchung, New Jersey. This collection contains records from the church's inception onward including vital statistics, historical information, and administrative records. On March 12, 1974, an electrical fire destroyed the sanctuary building, eventually resulting in a decision to dissolve the Watchung Congregational Church. Most members moved to the Union Congregational Church or the First Congregational Church, both in Montclair. When the property was sold in 1977, the proceeds of the sale went to those two congregations.
Watchung Congregational Church (Montclair, N.J.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
The original collection was donated in 1977. Additional materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by Timothy Crist in 2024; 2024-45.
Historical Information
In 1903, the Watchung Congregational Church emerged out of the need for a Congregational church around Watchung, New Jersey. The first service took place on January 18, 1903, in one of the four classrooms of Watchung School. In 1904 the church acquired a new property to hold services and Sunday School. By December 5th of 1905, the church was admitted into the association of Congregational Churches. In 1916 the church added to its property a community building which enabled educational, dramatic, and recreational pursuits.
Shortly following a remodel of the church building in 1951, sometime between 1954 and 1965, members voted to become part of the United Church of Christ. After this vote, the diaconate became the single governing board of the church. On March 12, 1974, an electrical fire destroyed the sanctuary building, eventually resulting in a decision to dissolve the Watchung Congregational Church. Most members moved to the Union Congregational Church or the First Congregational Church, both in Montclair. When the property was sold in 1977, the proceeds of the sale went to those two congregations.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records from the Watchung Congregational Church including vital statistics, historical information, and administrative records.
Arrangement
The Watchung Congregational Church records have been arranged into the three series listed below. Within each series materials have been arranged first by topic, and then in chronological order by start date.
Series 1: Vital statistics, 1903-1975
Series 2: Administrative records, 1903-1976
Series 3: Historical information, 1934-1982
Church buildings.; Church history.; Church records and registers.; Corporate minutes.; Vital statistics.; Watchung Congregational Church (Montclair, N.J.)
- Vital Statistics, 1903 1975; 1903-1975; 8 Folders; 2 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains vital statistics and includes records on baptisms, marriages, letters of dismission, and general registers.
  - Register, 1903 1956; 1903-1956 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Register, 1954 1965; 1954-1965 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Register, 1957 1976; 1957-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters of dismission, 1905 1935; 1905-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters of dismission, 1935 1949; 1935-1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters of dismission, 1949 1957; 1949-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters of dismission, 1957 1975; 1957-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baptism records, 1934 1940; 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marriage records, 1908 1940; 1908-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Marriage records, 1951 1975; 1951-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Administrative records, 1903 1976; 1903-1976; 9 Folders; 3 Volumes
  This series consists of administrative records and includes a copy of the certificate of incorporation, Watchung Congregational Society meeting minutes, clerk's books, and reports.
  - Watchung Congregational Society minutes, 1903 1938; 1903-1938 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Watchung Congregational Society records, 1904 1911; 1904-1911 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clerk's book, 1903 1919; 1903-1919 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Clerk's book, 1919 1936; 1919-1936 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Certificate of incorporation, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes and reports, 1939 1976; 1939-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual reports, 1940 1945; 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Loyalty Sunday fliers, 1950 1960; 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brochure for Candidates Considering the Pastorate, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes and reports (1 of 2), 1967 1975; 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes and reports (2 of 2), 1967 1975; 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Religious census, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Historical Information, 1934 1982; 1934-1982; 4 Folders
  This series contains historical information and includes three historical sketches, and multiple newspaper articles.
  - Photocopies of newspaper clippings, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photocopies of histories, 1943 1953; 1943, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Montclair Times church fire article, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Strength Inherited: Watchung Congregational Church, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)